<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Italian, by the most Reuerend father, Marc' Antony de Dominis, Archb. of Spalato, the first Sunday in Aduent, anno 1617. In the Mercers Chappel in London, to the Italians in that city, and many other honorable auditors then assembled. Vpon the 12. verse of the 13. chapter to the Romanes, being part of the Epistle for that day. First published in Italian by the author, and thereout translated into English</title>
            <title>Predica fatta da Monsr. Marc' Antonio de Dominis, Arcivo. di Spalato. English</title>
            <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845440</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845440</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1094:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Italian, by the most Reuerend father, Marc' Antony de Dominis, Archb. of Spalato, the first Sunday in Aduent, anno 1617. In the Mercers Chappel in London, to the Italians in that city, and many other honorable auditors then assembled. Vpon the 12. verse of the 13. chapter to the Romanes, being part of the Epistle for that day. First published in Italian by the author, and thereout translated into English</title>
                  <title>Predica fatta da Monsr. Marc' Antonio de Dominis, Arcivo. di Spalato. English</title>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 81, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XVII. [1617]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Predica fatta da Monsr. Marc' Antonio de Dominis, Arcivo. di Spalato.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" and a woodcut; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Italian --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10339:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10339:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN ITALIAN, <hi>By the most Reuerend father,</hi> MARC ANTONY DE DOMINIS, Archb. of SPALATO, the firſt Sunday in Aduent, ANNO 1617.</p>
            <p>In the Mercers Chappel in London, to the <hi>Italians</hi> in that City, and many other Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable auditors then aſſembled.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 12. Verſe of the 13. Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> being part of the Epiſtle for that day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First publiſhed in</hi> ITALIAN <hi>by the Author, and thereout Tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by IOHN BILL, M.DC.XVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10339:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10339:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The night is paſſed, the day is at hand: Let vs therefore caſt off the workes of darkneſſe, and let vs put on the armour of light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F in this preſent drooping, and dead time of the yeere it delights a man, after the longſome night, to behold the day, though moſt-what cloudie, and at the ſhorteſt, much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull muſt the ſame be in the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable ſeaſons of the yeere, when the Sunne being in his greateſt ſtrength, affoordeth vs long, and faire dayes, fit for many worthy employments. But if, immediately vpon one of theſe chill and tedious nights, there ſhould ſhine foorth an vnexpected Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſday, which were neuer to be intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any night, or winter, or irkeſomneſſe at all, how would we be taken with delight, and admiration. The bleſſed Apoſtle Saint
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10339:3"/>Paul, after a very long &amp; many wayes dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome night, obſeruing, that now there had approached both to himſelfe, and to his deare brethren in Chriſt, a day in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects moſt happie, which was to expect no night at all, with this congratulatory ſpeech addreſſeth himſelfe to them, and giueth this watchword, ſaying, <hi>Nox praeceſsit; dies autem appropinquauit. The night is paſt, and the day is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the ſame ſentence may I fitly now furniſh my ſelfe, in this my firſt ſpeech, for an affectionate congratulation with you, my beloued brethren of <hi>Italie,</hi> and you my other auditors heere aſſembled to heare me. Foraſmuch as I haue at this time ſet my ſelfe no other taske, then to preſent in common mine owne ioyes, together with yours: my comming into theſe parts being, not to teach others, but to be taught my ſelfe, not to be an inſtructor, but to be inſtructed, and ſet aright. Now therefore hauing vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for ſatisfying the deſire, and pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of many, to ſpeake vnto you this day, and happily againe hereafter in the like
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10339:3"/>maner, I intend to hold my ſelfe to my wonted ſimplicity of preaching, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſtile, and to keepe aloofe from all choice phraſes, and affected ſtreines of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian elegancies, contenting my ſelfe rather to worke vpon the affections, then to ſatisfie the vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>I reſume therefore my Text, and ſay, <hi>Nox praeceſsit &amp;c. The night is paſt, the day commeth on. Let vs caſt off the workes of darknes, and put on the armour of light.</hi> Theſe foure briefe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſhall be the foure points of this preſent Exerciſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1 The firſt of the diuerſe myſticall, and ſpirituall nights, which are ſayd to be paſſed.</item>
               <item n="2">2 The ſecond of the diuerſe dayes oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to thoſe nights.</item>
               <item n="3">3 The third of putting off darkneſſe.</item>
               <item n="4">4 The fourth of putting on light.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>BVt before we vndertake the handling of theſe particulars, we are to preſent our ſelues in hearty praiers before the throne of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie, humblie requeſting our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, firſt to caſt the tender eyes of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10339:4"/>his mercy vpon his vniuerſall holy Church, and that it would pleaſe him by his ſpirit to vnite all Chriſtian Churches in the onely, true, pure, and holy faith, to combine them in perfect charity, to extinguiſh all diſuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to make vp all rents and ſchiſmes, to mollifie all hardned hearts, that they may caſt off their obſtinacie, and lay aſide all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reſpects, and deſeignes; that ſo all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles, hindering this ſo important vnion, may be remooued. Let vs pray for all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, that God would kindle in their hearts a feruent zeale to procure the generall reformation of the Church, and to ſet forward this holy vnion. In ſpeciall let vs pray for his moſt excellent Maieſtie of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> the true Defender of the true ancient, pure, &amp; holy, Catholique, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique faith: that God would in his owne hands hold his Maieſties heart, and continue ſtill turning, and plying it to his holy ſeruice, and to the accompliſhing of whatſoeuer tendeth to the ſpirituall, and temporall good of this moſt flouriſhing kingdome: that he would giue him a long
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10339:4"/>and a proſperous life, and finally put Satan, and all his other enemies vnder his feet. He bleſſe with all proſperity the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: Hee with his grace aſſiſt the moſt noble Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> eſpecially in theſe his tender yeeres, which vſually hold faſt the firſt good impreſſions; Infuſe, O Lord, into him feare of thy holy name, zeale of pietie, and religion, and the imitation of the ſolide and true Regall vertues of his Father. Pray we likewiſe for the moſt Illuſtrious, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector <hi>Fredericke,</hi> Count Palatine, and the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that God will make them fruitfull parents of a bleſſed offpring. Pray we alſo for the moſt renowmed State of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> that God would deliuer them from all their enemies, and preſerue them in their full liberty. God enlighten the mindes of thoſe wiſe and graue Senatours, and giue them vnderſtanding to know, and courage to execute whatſoeuer ſhall make for the aduancement of his glory, ſeruice, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Pray wee for the moſt honourable Counſellers, Gouernours, and Magiſtrates whatſoeuer of theſe kingdomes, that God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10339:5"/>would powre downe of his ſpirit plentifully vpon them, for the good guidance and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of this people. Let vs pray for all Prelates, Prieſts, and Miniſters of the holy Vniuerſall Church: In ſpeciall for thoſe that mannage the ſpirituall affaires in theſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, that they may performe their ſeruice to God, and to his holy Church with true zeale, and an vpright heart. Let vs pray for all the Nobility of theſe kingdomes, that God would keepe and maintaine them in their due fealtie toward God, and toward their King, and alwayes incline their hearts to good, and holy deſeignes. Pray we for all the people, that God would bleſſe them with all aboundance of ſpirituall, and temporall bleſſings. Laſtly let vs pray, that God would grant me ſuch grace, that, in publiſhing his ſacred word, I may both my ſelfe reape in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly true ſpirituall fruit, and reach foorth the like to this honourable audience. For all theſe things let vs deuoutly ſay that Prayer, which our Lord IESVS CHRIST hath taught vs. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10339:5"/>
               <p>THE no leſſe enlightned, then belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Diſciple of our Sauiour, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle, Euangeliſt, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, intending to compriſe in a very ſmall abridgement, the whole doctrine of the Goſpel, and to ſhew what was the aime, and ſcope, whereto all Euangelicall preaching muſt tend, inſiſted vpon two briefe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions combined together, but by relation of contrariety; the one affirmatiue, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther negatiue, both concerning God. And before he ſets them forth, in his firſt Epiſtle he premiſeth a faire troope to make way for them. <hi>Quod fuit ab initio &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>That which was from the beginning, which wee haue heard, which we haue ſeene with our eyes, which we haue looked vpon, and our hands haue handled of the word of life. For the life was manifeſted, and wee haue ſeene it, and beare witnes, and ſhew vnto you that eternall life, which was with the Father, and was manifeſted vnto vs.</hi> And yet, not content with this great preparation, hee repeateth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſaith, <hi>That, which wee haue ſeene, and heard, declare we vnto you, that yee alſo may haue fellowſhippe with vs; and our fellowſhippe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10339:6"/>is with the Father, and with his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Now therefore hauing awakened vs with touching vpon the exceeding benefit of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiued into fellowſhippe with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles, by receiuing that, which hee thus propoundeth to vs; let him ſay at the laſt, what this is of ſo great importance, which was from the beginning, that is, from beyond all eternity: which the holy Apoſtles had heard, and handled with their hands, which ſhould bring vs eternall life, and which they were to preach, and teach thorowout the world: Let him ſay, and declare it in a word, we will heare it. <hi>Ethaec eſt annunciatio &amp;c. This is the meſſage, which we haue heard, and declare vnto you.</hi> Well: Bleſſed Saint Iohn, we are ready, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to heare this your admirable and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious meſſage: vnfold at length that, which you haue heard, and learnt, and receiued to report vnto vs. Behold, heere it followeth in few words: <hi>Quoniam Deus lux eſt; &amp; in eo tenebrae non ſunt vllae; That God is light, and in him there is no darkenes at all.</hi> Behold this is the abſtract, and ſumme of our faith, That God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10339:6"/>is light without darkneſſe. Therefore our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation confiſteth in receiuing this light, and in caſting out darkneſſe. <hi>Deus lux eſt &amp;c. God is light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If God himſelfe be light, what maruaile then, that hee ſo delighteth to imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe about light. The firſt inward Word, which God from all eternity brought forth within himſelfe, what was it but his ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, eternall word, his only begotten ſonne, whom we know to be <hi>Lumen de lumine,</hi> light of light. <hi>Lux vera, quae illuminat &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.</note> 
                  <hi>The true light, which enlightneth euery man that commeth into the world.</hi> Likewiſe the firſt externall word of God, which he vttered out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after an eternity of ſilence, was this, <hi>Fiat lux, Let there be light.</hi> Light, a creature ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of the Creator, that he thought good to beſtow this one and onely quality as a ſufficient dowrie on the heauenly bodies, which are the moſt noble and exalted crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in all the ranke of ſenſible ſubſtances. But will ye yet further obſerue, how great a friend God is to light, and enemie to dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Behold hee would not ſuffer his new
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10339:7"/>framed materiall world to remaine without light ſo much as the three firſt dayes of the Creation.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.1.</note> The Sunne and Moone the two great lights, together with the other leſſer lights of the ſtarres, were to bee made the fourth day: and yet, becauſe in this meane while <hi>darknes was vpon the face of the deepe,</hi> in the firſt diſtinguiſhing of things out of the confuſed lumpe, God, as enemie of this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſayd, <hi>Let there be light; and there was light.</hi> Light the firſt borne of all the viſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: light, which hath no poſitiue contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in nature: light, which diſplayeth it ſelfe to all, and maketh all things elſe manifeſt: light, which pierceth euery tranſparent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy though moſt ſolide: light, the ioy of the eyes, and comfort of euery afflicted heart. <hi>Quale gaudium eſt mihi, qui in tenebris ſedeo, &amp; lumen coeli nen video? What ioy can I take, that ſit in darknes, and behold not the light of heauen?</hi> ſayd good old <hi>Tobia,</hi> when hee was blinde: Light, which transfuſeth it ſelfe in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: light, which cannot be defiled by the touch of things impure: light, which giueth life to all colours, and actuateth them: light,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10339:7"/>the mother of all beauties, and ornaments of this ſenſible world. The Rainebow ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a goodly ſhew being guarded, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with ſo many, and ſo amiable colours, which in truth are nothing els, but the light of the Sunne reflected from dewie clouds, and by diuers compoſures of more, or leſſe opacity reduced to ſuch variety of colours. And generally al colours, which cloath with ſuch beauty the beſt viſible bodies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them to the eie with delight, what are they elſe, but mixtures of the lightſome elements with the obſcure. To conclude, light may by way of reſemblance, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation be accompted a diuine thing, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>God is light, and in him there is no darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> And therefore as ſoone, as God had cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the light, the pen of the Holy Ghoſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, that <hi>God ſaw the light that it was good, and diuided the light from the darkneſse.</hi> Vpon the atchieuement of euery other daies work, the Scripture cloſeth vp with this, <hi>Et vidit Deus, quod eſſet bonum; And God ſaw that it was good.</hi> But vpon the worke of the firſt day, wholly imployed in creating light only, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10339:8"/>addition is more ſpeciall; <hi>Et vidit Deus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, quod eſset bona; And God ſaw the light that it was good.</hi> But as for darkeneſſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interchangeablie to accompany the light for the bringing in of night, indeed there followeth Gods both ſeparation, and nomination of them both; <hi>Diuiſit Deus, &amp; vocauit Deus: God ſeparated the light from the darkneſſe, and God calleth the light Day, and the darkneſſe Night.</hi> But vpon this the Scripture doth not adde, that <hi>God ſaw that it was good;</hi> becauſe (it is S.
<note place="margin">Aug. de Gen. ad lit. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtines</hi> argute collection) God, as a ſpeciall louer of the light and hater of darknes, gaue to the light only this appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and praiſe, <hi>Quod erat bona,</hi> that it was good. But of the day and night coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he would affoord no ſuch commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, leſt he ſhould giue to night and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the aduancement of goodnes. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is cleare; for that <hi>Deus lux eſt, God is light,</hi> and in him there is no darknes, and hee it is, that dwelleth in that light, which no man can approach vnto.</p>
               <p>Well therefore might S. <hi>Paul</hi> frame this his congratulation with the faithfull vnder
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10339:8"/>the metaphore of light, and darkeneſſe, day, and night; <hi>Nox praeceſsit, dies autem appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquauit;</hi> telling this, as moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble newes, that a very longſome, and irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome night was ouerblowne, and that a goodly faire day then had ouertaken them. <hi>Procopius</hi> writeth, that neere to the Pole, where the nights endure diuers moneths long, the inhabitants in the end of ſuch a night, at ſuch time as the Sunne vſeth to render himſelfe to their view, get vp their higheſt mountaines, ſtriuing to haue the firſt view of that moſt deſired creature: and no ſooner doe they eſpie it, but they adorne themſelues in their beſt attire, and with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ioy and embraces congratulate, ſaying, Behold the Sunne, the Sunne appeares; and ſo they inuite and feaſt one another. And all this vpon the view of the materiall Sun onely. Another maner of feaſt, and ioy it is, to which the Apoſtle heere doeth incite, and inuite. Whileſt in a myſticall, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſenſe he proclaymeth to vs, that, The night is paſſed, and the day come. Where he pointeth at the miſeries of the continuall,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10339:9"/>dreadfull, and hideous nights then ouerpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of the long &amp; happie daies brought vnto vs by that Sunne, which knowes no going downe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nox praeceſsit.</hi> Three kindes of nights are heere vnderſtood by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> whereof he ioyed that they were ouerpaſſed. The firſt the night of ignorance, the ſecond of ſinne, the third of negligence. To theſe, in regard of our ſelues, and theſe times, I will adde a fourth, the night of errors. So that of theſe the two firſt goe before the receiuing of the faith, namely the night of blinding igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and tyrannizing ſinne; the other two follow the faith receiued, namely ſtupifying negligence, and infecting error.</p>
               <p>Yee haue often reade, and many of you conſidered the ſtrange maner of ſpeech vſed in the holy Scriptures, in the diſtinction of the ſix dayes of the Creation. <hi>And the euening, and the morning, were the firſt day:</hi> Euery day hath its night, the day goeth before, and the night followeth after, the morning maketh way for the euening. Surely nature requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that the habite ſhould precede the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10339:9"/>Whereupon I conceiue not to what purpoſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> puſled himſelfe, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled naturall Philoſophie, by ſhouldring in after Matter &amp; Forme, Priuation for a third principle of naturall bodies, vnleſſe hee meant hereby, that whatſoeuer is generated, maketh a paſſage from not beeing vnto bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But if ſo, yet this not beeing might well bee termed negation rather then priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Or rather by priuation; perhaps the Philoſopher would ſignifie vnto vs the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination of matter to receiue a new forme, which appetite is very improperly called priuation. Now, as for the text <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt veſpere, &amp; mane &amp;c.</hi> It is enough for vs, that it, being a phraſe meerely extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, importeth a myſtery. Too tedious ſhould I bee, if I ſhould heere propound all the diuers opinions of the holy Fathers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe words. But for as much as ſerueth my purpoſe, I doubt not, but that God in his intention was willing to make man wholly diurnall, and no whit participating of the night: For hee created him right and iuſt, and endued him with ſuch gifts, whereby
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10339:10"/>hee might, if hee would, haue made to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to all his poſterity, a perpetuall ſpirituall day, which ſhould neuer haue ſeene any night at all. But God (inaſmuch as hee foreſaw, that wretched man would within a few houres after his creation aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the light, and caſt himſelfe headlong into darkneſſe) mooued with compaſſion of him, in his determination prouided a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by deſtinating for mans ſake his owne ſonne, the true light, and ſunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bring them from darkeneſſe to light, from night to day. And therefore it ioyes my heart to thinke how God ordayned that (beſides other myſterious interpretations) euen for the ſhadowing out this then hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den myſtery, the Scripture deſcribing the beginning of the world ſhould ſpeake in this wiſe, <hi>Factum est veſpere, &amp; mane,</hi> intimating firſt the euening or night of mans miſery, and then the morning or day of his redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion following. For as for his firſt eſtate of integrity and light, it was ſo ſhort, that it is not to bee accounted for a day in this kinde. And ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> here not varying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10339:10"/>contemplation, reioyceth that that night is paſſed, and this day arriued; ſaying, <hi>Nox prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit, dies autem appropinquauit.</hi> The night is paſt, the day is at hand.</p>
               <p>By the firſt of theſe nights I meane igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or ſmall knowledge of things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God. But heere it may bee obiected if S. <hi>Paul</hi> had written this Epiſtle to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted Gentiles onely, well might he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by this night ignorance; but writing alſo to the Iewes then in Rome conuerted to Chriſtianity, it ſeemeth that they could not then be taken to liue in darkeneſſe, and in the night of ignorance.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> For <hi>Notus in Iudaea De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. In Iurie is God knowne, his name is great in Iſrael. Iuda was his Sanctuary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 114.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and Iſrael his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</hi> Which alſo was ſignified in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 10.</note> when there was palpable darkneſſe thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all that land, but in the land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> where the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwelt, there was cleere light.
<note place="margin">Iſai 9.2.</note> The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpake onely of the Gentiles, when he ſayd, <hi>The people that walked in darkeneſſe, haue ſeene a great light, and they that dwelt in the land of the ſhadow of death, vpon them hath the light ſhined.</hi> The Iewes had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10339:11"/>the Law,
<note place="margin">Cap. 3.</note> and the Prophets. <hi>To them</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth in this epiſtle) <hi>were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the oracles of God.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, ſeeing that S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath made no ſuch ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor diſtinction betweene Iew and Gentile, but hath expreſly proclaimed, that <hi>the Goſpell is the power of God vnto ſaluation to euery beleeuer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to the Iew firſt, and then to the Greeke. For by it the righteouſnes of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uecled from faith to faith;</hi> He intendeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that aſwell the Iew, as Gentile by the meanes of the Goſpel only hath attained the true and perfect knowledge of God. So then the Goſpell being this light, and day, for certaine, <hi>Nox praeceſsit, The night is paſſed,</hi> not to the Gentiles onely, but alſo to the Iewes. For if wee conſider the knowledge, which was to be found either in <hi>Iurie,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles before the comming of Chriſt, that, in reſpect of the knowledge of God and of heauenly things, was very ſmall and ſhallow, whereupon it might worthily be called night in compariſon of the cleare day of the Goſpell. As for the Law, who knowes not that it was <hi>Vmbra futurorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10339:11"/>ſhadow of things to come,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it? And if it were a ſhadow, it did partake of the nature of night. In the Old Teſtament the myſtery of the Trinity is very obſcurely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded vnto. And as for that of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it had beene ordinarily vnderſtood of the Iewes, they would not haue made ſuch reſiſtance againſt Chriſt. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe both Iew, &amp; Gentile before the comming of Chriſt were very weake, and wanted the perfect knowledge of God, S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere ſayeth to them both, <hi>Nox prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit,</hi> The night is gone. The Prophet <hi>Iſai</hi> foretelleth it, and the Euangeliſt S. <hi>Matthew</hi> confirmeth it, what was the meaſure of the true knowledge of God as well among the Iewes, as Gentiles, at the time when the Redeemer came into the world.
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>A bruiſed reede ſhall hee not breake, and the ſmoaking flaxe ſhall he not quench.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt did finde Iudaea to bee a broken reede, wherby is inſinuated, (according to the expoſition of my countryman Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>) that the Iew was not at that time ſo loudly ſounding in ſetting forth the glory of God, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10339:12"/>they were. And in truth that people then (as alſo at this day farre more miſerably) was more guided by the ſuperſtitious traditions of their vaine Rabbines, then by the holy Scriptures. Wherewith our Sauiour alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided them, ſaying, <hi>Why doe ye by your tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions tranſgreſſe Gods Commandement?</hi> And the very ſame now adayes is to bee found vnder the Papacie; where much more accompt is made of the Popes commandements, then of Gods; The committing of adultery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reputed galantery, but the eating of fleſh vpon a Friday, a ſacriledge worthy of fagot and fire. As for the Gentiles, Chriſt found them to be <hi>linum fumigans,</hi> ſmothering flaxe, not altogether put out, but ſomwhat ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by reaſon of that ſmall and weake knowledge of God, which the glimpſe of the Law of Nature affoorded them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in concluſion, an vniuerſall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon night did ouerſpread all, both Iew, and Gentile. And if <hi>Zachary</hi> the father of the great <hi>Baptiſt</hi> had not acknowledged the nightly darkeneſſe, wherein both himſelfe, and the reſt of that people remained, hee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10339:12"/>would not haueſung, that Chriſt was <hi>the day ſpring from on High, To giue light to them that ſit in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death, and to guide our feet into the way of peace.</hi> Surely that,
<note place="margin">Iob 36.32.</note> which we read in the booke of <hi>Iob</hi> may be truely vnderſtood as well of Iudaiſme, as of Gentiliſme; And this it is, <hi>In manibus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondit lucem, &amp; praecepit ei, vt rurſus adueniat; He bideth the light in his hands, and commandeth it to come againe.</hi> Whereby is giuen vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that God, before that hee ſent the Light of his owne Sonne into the world, did hold the light of the knowledge of God claſped vp in his hand, ſo that, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſome glimmering beames darted foorth through the clifts from betweene the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, yet he did reſerue the wyde opening of his hand till the fulneſſe of time; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then he commanded this light <hi>vtrurſus adueniat,</hi> to come againe at that time when S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſhortly after proclaime, <hi>Nox praeceſsit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if by this night wee will vnderſtand the true and totall darkeneſſe of Infidelity, then are wee to ſay, that the Apoſtle doeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10339:13"/>not heere meane the ancient by-paſt times before the comming of Chriſt, but rather the very time wherein our Sauiour liued in his fleſh vpon the earth, and when the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel was firſt publiſhed by the Apoſtles. In a word heere is eſpecially to bee vnderſtood that eſtate, wherein the new Chriſtians of Rome (aſwell Iewes, as Gentiles) were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before their conuerſion to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which was indeed an vtter darkneſſe of night. What els were the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles of that time in Rome, and throughout the whole world, but Idolaters? And as for the Iewes, had not they then crucified our Lord and Sauiour? Had not they then reiected their Meſſias? Did not they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remain with the veile ouer their hearts?
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> And what greater infidelitie, then not to receiue Chriſt? Nay, to perſecute him in his members? Euen in this night S. <hi>Paul</hi> accounted himſelfe to haue bin: And worthily; For he teſtifieth of himſelfe, that he <hi>was formerly a blaſphemer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. Galat. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and a perſecuter, and iniunious; and that hee perſecuted the Church of God beyond meaſure, and waſted it.</hi> Out of the lumpe of theſe hardened, and blinded
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10339:13"/>Iewes, came the remnant of theſe, which embraced the Chriſtian religion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with good reaſon of theſe, as ſo of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Nox praeceſsit,</hi> To vs, and in ſpeciall to me, the night is paſſed.</p>
               <p>The ſecond night, whereof <hi>S. Paul</hi> would here be vnderſtood, is the night of reigning ſinne; and this was moſt common both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes, and Gentiles. How hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and filthy the enormities of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles were, eſpecially in Rome, may appeare by the particular, and euen loathſome cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue recorded by <hi>S. Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle. <hi>Wherefore God gaue them vp to their hearts luſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto vncleannes, to defile their owne bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues: who turned the trueth of God into a lye, and worſhipped, and ſerued the creature. Wherefore God gaue them vp to vile affections</hi> of moſt abominable ſinnes. <hi>And deliuered them vp to a reprobate minde, to doe thoſe things which are not conuenient. Being filled with all vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, formcation, wickednes, couetouſnes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſnes, full of enuy, murther, debate, deceit, malignity, whisperers, backbiters, haters of God, despitefull, proud, boasters, inuenters of euil things,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10339:14"/>diſobedient to parents, without vnderstanding, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant breakers, without naturall affection, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable, vnmercifull.</hi> Surely either <hi>S. Paul</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically deſcribeth the enormous ſinnes, and moſt corrupt maners of Rome, as it ſtands in our times: Or els Rome, as now it is, and hath bene for ſome ages paſt, hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to be in all points like to heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Rome, as it was in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> time. The manifold wickedneſſes of the now Rome could not bee more exactly pencelled, and drawen out to life, then by that, which the Apoſtle here particularizeth. O dreadfull night! ô palpable darkneſſe! ô vntollerable blindneſſe! Verely ſuch impieties, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities conclude, that as yet the firſt night of the want of the knowledge of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth there, Inaſmuch as ſo hidious ſinnes are proper to the Heathen, as the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle witneſſeth, <hi>Sicut &amp; Gentes; As the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 4.5. Epheſ. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>which know not God. Non ambuletis ſicut &amp; Gentes &amp;c. That ye walke not as the Gentiles walke, in the vanity of their minds, hauing the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10339:14"/>of the blindneſſe of their heart: Who being paſt feeling, haue giuen themſelues ouer vnto laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciuiouſneſſe, to worke all vncleannes with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines.</hi> Certainly ſuch life and maners, which are very ordinary and common in the Court of Rome (yet I except whatſoeuer good men are there) doe inferre, that according to the Apoſtles intimation, the knowledge of God, and hope of euerlaſting life is not to be found among them. <hi>Edamus, bibamus, cras moriemur.</hi> Let vs eat and drinke to day, for we ſhall die to morrow. And yet they moſt of all ſhould open their eyes, and mend their maners. Thus therefore to the Gentiles made Chriſtians, <hi>Nox praeceſsit,</hi> The night of grieuous offences is paſt. Neither yet were the Iewes out of the ſhade of this night; <hi>Qui alios doces, teipſum non doces?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelfe? Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteale, doeſt thou ſteale? Thou that ſayſt a man ſhould not commit adultery, doeſt thou commit adultery? Thou that abhorreſt idols, doest thou commit ſacriledge? Thou that makeſt thy boaſt of the Law, through breaking the Law, diſhonoureſt thou God? For the name of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10339:15"/>is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is no difference,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>for all haue ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God.</hi> All therfore were ouer clouded with this night of moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes. <hi>Wee haue prooued both Iewes and Gentiles to be all vnder ſinne, as it is written, They are all gone out of the way, they are all become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, there is none that doth good no not one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is the night? Nothing elſe, but the abſence of the Sunne. And what elſe, but ſinne,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.</note> driueth the Sunne of righteouſneſſe Chriſt Ieſus from our ſoules. <hi>In maleuolam animam non intrabit Sapientiae, nec habitabit in corpore ſubdito peccatis: Wiſedome will not enter into a malicious ſoule, nor dwell in a body ſubiected to ſinne.</hi> What is the night? It is the ſhadow of the earth interpoſing it ſelfe betweene vs and the Sunne. And what elſe is ſinne, but a darke, and groſſe obſtacle intercepting the beames of the inuiſible Sunne, ſo that they cannot pierce downe to vs?
<note place="margin">Iſay 59.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Your trangreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue made a ſeparation betweene God and you, and your ſinnes haue hid his face from you.</hi> What is the night? It is a ſeaſon vnfit for trauailers other then thoſe, that are willing to looſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10339:15"/>their way, and to aduenture their neckes in headlong downefals. And what elſe is ſinne, but a wandring from the way that leadeth to heauen, and a downeright gallop into the pit of hell?
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 81.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Dimiſi eos ſecundum deſideria cordis ipſorum; ibunt in adinuentionibus ſuis. I gaue them vp to their owne hearts luſts, and they will walke in their owne inuentions.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 18.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Improbus cum in profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum venerit peccatorum contemnit: ſed ſequitur eum ignominia &amp; opprobrium. When the wicked man commeth into the depth of ſinne, he groweth to contempt, but ſhame and reproach follow him.</hi> Of this night alſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere ſayd, <hi>The night is paſſed:</hi> For they were now waſhed and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their ſinnes, and had their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers alſo mortified; as I ſhall touch in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the day oppoſite to this night.</p>
               <p>The third night, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere had an eye vnto, was the night of negligence, and dulneſſe. Nay it may ſeeme, that hee had principall reſpect heereunto: For being that hee ſpake to the Romanes already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to Chriſt, whoſe faith alſo hee ſayd to haue <hi>beene ſpoken of thorowout the whole world;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> they therefore were out of the night of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10339:16"/>delity. Of whom alſo he had ſayd, that they <hi>were freely inſtified by Gods grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, that is in Ieſus Chriſt. — by faith in his blood, to declare his righteouſneſſe for the remiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes paſt.</hi> And therefore now they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtified, and out of the night of ſinne, yet the Apoſtle in this chapter ſaith to them, <hi>It is now high time for vs to awake from ſleepe.</hi> They were therefore yet aſleepe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in a certaine kinde of night, though they had ouerpaſſed the two former nights, whereof I haue ſpoken. And of this third night the Apoſtles meaning is, that it is not entirely paſſed ouer: but he exhorteth them to endeuor, and ſtriue to ſhake off this ſleep, and to driue away this night alſo, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Gods grace they had worne out the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two nights of ignorance, and of ſinne, He therefore vrgeth them to rouze vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from ſpirituall ſloth, and drowſineſſe, and to become watchfull in things pertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their ſaluation. This night will bee more euident by our mention of the day op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite heereunto.</p>
               <p>I paſſe therefore to the fourth night, from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10339:16"/>which God out of his infinite bounty hath freed vs in theſe times. Concerning which, I may ſay with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> on mine owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and yours (my brethren of <hi>Italy,</hi> whom God hath bleſſed with the cleare light of the trueth) <hi>Nox praeceſsit, The night is past.</hi> And for this I make ſuch congratulation as may ſerue, not to inſult vpon others, or proudly to glory in our ſelues, but to render due thankes to the Almighty, and to ſtirre vp our affections to compaſſionate our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who yet remaine in no ſmall danger, lying in the deepe darkſome night of many errors, though profeſſing the Chriſtian faith. Surely a night ſo much the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, in that thoſe poore ſoules deeme themſelues onely to enioy the Light, and dreame that all others, who adhere not to their part, remaine in darkeneſſe,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Et dicunt bonum malum &amp;c. And call good euill, and euill good, accounting light to be darkneſſe, and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of God is ſayd to be <hi>Caſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum acies ordinata; An armie ſet in array.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 6.3. Iob 7.</note> And in truth the whole <hi>life of man is a warfare vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10339:17"/>earth.</hi> But this warfare of the Church, and this mighty Armie in my opinion may bee more fitly reſembled to an <hi>Armada</hi> on the Sea, then to a march on the land. In which regard the Church is called, <hi>A Merchants ſhip bringing food from a farre.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 31.14.</note> And our Sauiour Chriſt being in a ſhip did then moſt liuely repreſent his Church,
<note place="margin">Luke 5.3.</note> as is very elegantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the holy Fathers. Chriſt hath his Nauie of many ſhips of warre, that is, a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of many particular Churches, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is the Head, and Generall. Againſt this Nauy there are in the ſea of this world open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet out many other ſhips of warre vnder the conduct of the Diuell, which are the troopes of diabolical ſects, and ſuperſtitious Infidels, the enemies of Chriſt. And in this warfare I, to my great griefe, behold the ſhips that are vnder the ſame Captaine, and Commander our Sauiour Chriſt, to purſue one another with no leſſe, nay perhaps with more hatred, then if they were indeed the ſhips of the enemy. The Church of Rome, and thoſe that follow the conduct of it, hate to the death the Reformed Churches. And
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10339:17"/>the Reformed hate them. I would faine ſet you right, my Auditors, in a great, and very common miſtake, if ſo bee that yee thinke the Reformed Religion to bee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion wholly differing from the Romane. The Religion of both is in the maine eſſentials and fundamentals the very ſame. Both haue the ſame Chriſt for their Lord and Maſter; both the ſame baptiſme; both are founded by the ſame Apoſtles; both haue and profeſſe the ſame Goſpel. But to the end wee may vnderſtand the eſtate of both the Romane, and Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I meane to hold my ſelfe to my ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſhips, and Nauigation. The voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Militant Church is a continuall ſayling in the Ocean of this world, amids a thouſand ſhelfes, and rockes, gulfes, and quickſands, where no ſhore, nor land at all is to bee ſeene. For our pilgrimage heere is in faith, and tendeth to the attaining of things inuiſible. <hi>Wee walke by faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and not by ſight. Wee ſee now through a glaſse darkly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> 
                  <hi>but then wee ſhall behold face to face.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.18.</note> Wee looke not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10339:18"/>on the things, that are ſeene, but on the things, that are not ſeene. For the things, which are ſeene, are temporall: but the things, which are not ſeene, are eternall.</hi> And the Nauigation, wherein the Church Militant is employed, tendeth to Spirituall things, <hi>which are not ſeene.</hi> And ſurely in Sea voyages amidſt the maine, where no land marke can bee ſeene for the direction of the ſhippe, the onely certaine meanes of guidance for Nauigation conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the vſing of a good Compaſſe, hauing a Needle well touched with the Loadſtone, as alſo in hauing a Ship mans Card, or Sea mappe iuſtly quartered, and coaſted. Hee that without theſe, or with a falſe Compaſſe, or Mappe, ſaileth out of all ſight of ſhoare, may bee ſaide to wander in vtter darkeneſſe, and midnight, though it be at noone-tide; And contrary wiſe, hee that is furniſhed with a true Compaſſe, though hee ſaile in the deepe of Sea, and of night, yet hee enioyeth the day, and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his paſſage at all occaſions. Now for the difference of the Reformed Shippes, and the Romane, it is not in the bottome,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10339:18"/>nor in the tackeling, but onely in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. The Romane ſhippe is a good Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, well built, not rotten, nor fallen in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; it is well furniſhed with Maſts, with Yards, with Cordage, with Cables, with Anchors; it hath an excellent Sea-mappe: the paſſengers, and common ſouldiers in it are all vnder the colours of one and the ſame Generall, our Sauiour Chriſt. And in theſe there is no difference betweene this Ship, and the reformed. But I finde one maine difference betweene them, whence alſo ariſe an innumerable other diſparities, and it is, that the Pilot, who ſits at the ſterne of the Romane ſhip, hauing throwne aſide the ordinary Compaſſe, and leauing the vſe of the approoued Sea-mappe, hath out of his owne capricious conceit deuiſed a new Card, and contriued a new-found Compaſſe of his owne, whoſe needle hath no aſpect toward the Pole, or touch at all of the Load-ſtone. Suteable alſo hereto hath he out of his owne head framed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Cardinall windes, which ſerue onely for his Card. Nay (which is worſe then
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10339:19"/>this) hee hath intruded into the poſſeſſion of gouerning the helmes of all the ſhippes, that roade in his company, and from euery of them hee hath taken away the vſe of the ordinary Compaſſe, and beating the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, and ouer awing them by tyranny (who otherwiſe would doe well, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their office aright) will haue no nay, but all thoſe ſhippes muſt daunce atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance after his. And ſo, for that hee vſeth no true Compaſſe, nor Carde, hee ringleads them all to wracke, and they follow him faſt enough without light through the thickeſt darkeneſſe.</p>
               <p>For the vnfolding of this Metaphore, I ſay in a word, that the Biſhoppe of Rome at this preſent, and for many ages paſt, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the trauailers true Sea-card, the holy Scriptures, and the vnmooueable North-Pole, the aime at Heauen and heauenly things; and propounding to himſelfe one onely Port, his owne greatneſſe, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall pompe, hath in his deuiſed Compaſſe quartered out his owne counterfeit windes, which muſt blow for that hauen; they are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10339:19"/>dominion ouer all other Churches, maſtery ouer the Keyes, infallibility of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and authoritie in things Temporall, euen ouer Princes. And as for the poore paſſengers, and common ſouldiers, who are tranſported, and blindly clapt vp vnder the hatches in theſe wandring ſhippes, he hath, to amuſe them, added in his falſe Card ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny baſtard windes, painted out in guilded, and flouriſhed lines; namely, our owne, and others merits, Inuocation of Saints, religious worſhip of Images, the treaſure of Indulgences, efficacie of Maſſes, and of Prieſtly abſolutions, <hi>Agnus Dei's,</hi> hallowed Beads, holy Water. By theſe, and other ſuch windes neuer found in the ancient true Compaſſes, and whereof the ancient Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots of the holy Church neuer heard any newes; by theſe blaſts will hee haue his followers to ſaile, whereby they are caried headlong into many moſt important er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. The onely cauſe of all this miſchiefe is that Archpilot. For if hee were remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or could bee perſwaded to leaue his owne monſtrous Chimericall Compaſſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10339:20"/>and to betake himſelfe to the vſuall and auncient guide, preſently defacing all thoſe falſe windes, verily the goodly fleete of the Catholique Church would eaſily bee ſet right, and holding the ſafe and ſure way (as the Reformed Companies haue done) would approach to the true hauen of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bliſſe. True it is, that theſe Reformed Churches, beeing miſledde by this wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring guide, did ſometime follow that vaine and deceitfull Compaſſe. But at length they haue better bethought themſelues and caſting out that ſtrange intruding Pilot, they haue yeelded vp their ſhippe to bee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by their owne true Steerſemen, ſuch as God himſelfe hath ordayned. And ſo vſing the infallible Card of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the true Compaſſe quartered out into the foure auncient Cardinall windes of the foure firſt generull Councels, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the vnder-windes of the holy Fathers, they make an happy voyage, and without wandring arriue at the appointed hauen of ſaluation. And this is the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble night of manifold errours, wherein ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10339:20"/>many poore ſoules ſuffer themſelues to bee hoodwinked, and lulled aſleepe: from which yet we are reſcued by the Almighty hand of God. And therefore let vs yeelde him all poſſible thankes, that <hi>This night is paſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I ſhould here enlarge my ſelfe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vpon the conſideration of theſe forged miſguiding blaſts, to diſplay all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar errors, which make this cloudie night, I might encomber my ſelfe in a confuſed <hi>Chaos,</hi> out of which I could not get in many dayes, much leſſe in the little portion of time allotted to this Exerciſe. Yet I can doe no leſſe now, then touch ſome of the moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and vniuerſall of them, out of which, as from a roote, all the particular errors doe ſpring.</p>
               <p>It is very much behoouefull to the Pope for the mainteining himſelfe in the forged greatneſſe of his vniuerſall Vicarſhip of Chriſt, to holde the people in the deepeſt darkneſſe of ignorance, and blindneſſe, that poſſibly may be. To this purpoſe one maine article, which he cauſeth to be taught in all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10339:21"/>the Churches ſubiect to him, ſtands him in great ſtead; namely, that, for the ſauing of mens ſoules, an implicite faith ſufficeth: whereby a man beleeueth all to be trueth, whatſoeuer the holy Catholique Romane Church beleeueth, and mainteineth. And by this meane the Pope layeth open a way for himſelfe to perſwade the ſilly people, already blinded with this credence, to beleeue, and receiue whatſoeuer hee impoſeth on them for his owne aduantage, and to make them admit for an article of faith, that hee is the onely vicar of Chriſt: that he cannot erre <hi>in cathedra,</hi> iudging out of his chaire: that he is the Lord paramount of the whole Church: that the keyes, and treaſure of holy Church are in his hands onely: that he hath power to depoſe Kings from their Thrones, and to diſcharge their ſubiects of their oath of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie; and infinite other ſuch fopperies: for the maintenance whereof, many wretches caſt away their ſoules. And by degrees it will come to that paſſe one day, that he will make himſelfe to be adored for a God vpon earth. By this engine of implicite faith, he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10339:21"/>barreth vp the way to the people, ſo that they cannot come to deſcry his inuentions, as long as they make it a ſcruple of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to examine, or conſider what trueth may bee in ſuch determinations, which are made by him for his owne aduantage onely, and not for their ſoules health. In this meane while the poore vulgar think, that they haue as much faith, as will ſerue for their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet in fine they will bee found to haue none at all. I beleeue that, which the Church beleeues. If I come not to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar articles, I yet beleeue nothing, but onely am in a diſpoſition to beleeue that, which the Church of Rome ſhall preſcribe mee, whether true, or falſe. Verely for any man to ſay, I beleeue that, which another man belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, is as much, as if he ſaid, I ſee that, which another man ſeeth, though my owne eyes be ſhut. And as no man can be ſaid to ſee, but only when the faculty of his owne ſight exerciſeth its operation vpon a particular obiect; ſo there is no actuall beleeuing, but when the vnderſtanding, and will doe actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally apprehend, and embrace the obiect of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10339:22"/>faith. There are vnder the Papacy, there are among the people many men endued by God with ſufficient iudgement and capacity to receiue good inſtruction in many myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our faith, if they had conuenient meanes and opportunity to learne them: but by reaſon of this implied faith, they are not only kept from learning thoſe things which they ought to know, but alſo a great number of them, and they not of the dullards, when they vnder a confuſed notion apprehend ſuch articles, frame to themſelues falſe, and erroneous conceipts of them. How many being enwrapped in this implicite faith, and being otherwiſe able diſtinctly to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that there are in Chriſt two diſtinct natures, and but one onely perſon, and that diuine, yet thinke that Chriſt is man by an humane perſon, and ſo are Neſtorians? How many are there, that beleeue Chriſt to be a meere man, and ſo are Arians? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beleeue that in Chriſt the diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane natures are confounded into one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Innumerable ſuch monſters of all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies may bee found vnder this <hi>Chimaera</hi> of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10339:22"/>inuolued faith. Beſides this, the more to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh theſe monſtrous errors, the Popes barre Chriſtian people from all means of learning the verities of the Chriſtian faith, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them the vſe of the holy Scriptures in ſuch language, as they may vnderſtand. For they are well aſſured, that the very vulgar would, by reading the Scriptures, diſcouer the manifold deuiſes, and trickes, wherwith the Popes, the Biſhops, the Preachers, the Prieſts, and Friars delude the ſimple people, to draw money out of their purſes, and to make themſelues be thought ſo many Gods. If the people might bee ſuffered to read the Scriptures in the mother tongue, they would finde, that all the twelue Apoſtles had the ſame charge, in all reſpects, equall with S. <hi>Peter,</hi> of planting, &amp; gouerning the Church. They would ſee, that in all the Bible there is nothing to bee found for S. <hi>Peters</hi> being at Rome, nor that hee hath left any ſpeciall charge with the Biſhop of Rome. They would be aduertiſed, that all Biſhops ſucceed the Apoſtles in equall power among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, without ſubiection of one to another:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10339:23"/>And that the vnion of holy Church conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the vnity of faith, and in charity, whereby all Churches are combined, and embrace one the other, and not in being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any one viſible head, but vnder Chriſt, the true, and only head of the Church. They would well know, that the Maſſe hath no other vſe, nor bringeth any other ſpirituall benefite, then to conſecrate the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Communion, and that only, when there are ſome, more, or leſſe to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that the pronouncing of ſome part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, and whiſpering the reſt, ſo that the people heares it not, is but a mockery. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that thoſe mimicall geſtures with the hands, leggs, and eyes ſerue for nothing, but to ſet the people on gazing in a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They would learne, that in the bread of the Euchariſt there is the true body of Chriſt Sacramentally, and after a wonderful maner, which to vs is inexplicable; but not in fleſh and bones, with eyes, hands, and feet. Neither ſhould they euer finde, that that conſecrated bread is to bee adored for God, euen as wee adore not the water which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10339:23"/>the blood of Chriſt in baptiſme, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, by the power of Gods grace, this water, and that bread in him that receiueth it worthily, worke maruelous ſpirituall effects in the ſoule. They would vnderſtand, that Purgatory, being not once named, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the Scriptures, is an inuention of the Prieſts, and Friars, to make men call for Maſſes, and to draw on paiments, and obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the reſcuing of ſoules out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. Which deuice rayſeth an income, whereby ſuch a ſwarme of idleſbies (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnprofitable to the Church, but alſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous) are maintained, liuing in iollity, and wallowing in all vncleanneſſe. Theſe, and many other like trueths would the people deſcrie, if they might read the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor would they ſuffer themſelues to be any longer deceiued, and fuddled vp in that darke cloud, and night of infolded faith. Much the eaſier alſo would they vnderſtand theſe things, if together with the Scriptures, diuers godly, and holy Bookes might bee ſuffered to come to their view, which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the impoſtures of the Papacie, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10339:24"/>lay down the true way to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet theſe Bookes are moſt falſly by the Pope, for his owne behoofe, declared to be hereticall, and prohibited, as peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that kind, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euer ſhewing particularly wherin theſe pretended hereſies conſiſt: Which are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding taught by the holy Fathers of the Church. But this is his refuge for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, leſt his errours ſhould bee diſcouered. And, as for ſo many ſoules running this way headlong into hell, that troubleth him not, may he the while hold vp his wordly pomp. And ſo much of the firſt generall error.</p>
               <p>Another generall error, wherewith the captiuated Churches in Italy, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elſewhere are ſeduced, is the perſwading of the ſimple people, that they obtaine infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible remiſſion of all their ſinnes committed after baptiſme, by vertue of certaine exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſenſible, and materiall actions, which are called Sacraments, and Sacramentals. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the common people being by nature prone, and haſty to ſuperſtition, and more willing, and ready to vndergoe externall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie performances, then inward duties diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10339:24"/>and diſtaſtful to fleſh and blood, put too much confidence in theſe outward ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, being in the meane time deſtitute of the true inward effect of deſired remiſſion of their ſinnes, and ſo the blinde being led by the blinde, both fall into the pit.</p>
               <p>The true Sacraments inſtituted by our Sauiour for remiſſion of ſinnes, are holy Baptiſme, and the ſacred Communion. And the only true and reall remedy, whereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, done after Baptiſme, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, is Repentance, which conſiſteth in true ſorrowing for ſinne, together with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to leaue ſinne by the aſſiſtance of Gods grace. But ſee how extrauagant the Papall doctrine is in this point: Namely, that it is neceſſary to confeſſe to a Prieſt all and euery of our ſinnes, one by one, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the circumſtances of them; and that thereupon preſently comes abſolution, which <hi>ex opere operato</hi> by vertue of the deed done, that is, infalliblie, by a Sacramentall operation, releaſeth the ſinne <hi>quantum ad cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam,</hi> as much as concernes the guiltineſſe of it: and as for an after-reckoning <hi>quantum ad
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10339:25"/>poenam,</hi> concerning the puniſhment, that is remitted by ſatisfaction enioined, or by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. This ſo mighty efficacy they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to Prieſtly abſolution, by vertue whereof they will that a ſinner preſently becommeth <hi>ex attrito contritus,</hi> that is to ſay, though he doe not truly and ſoundly repent him of his ſinnes, but conceiue a certaine ſleight and light ſorrow, out of feare onely of Gods puniſhments, and not out of hatred of ſinne, yet vpon the act of abſolution, hee enioyeth the benefit of remiſſion, as fully, as if he had true and entire repentance, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with hatred of ſinne. In this maner they breed vp a ſinner, and make him in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to cleaue faſt to his ſinnes, whileſt he flattereth himſelfe, that Confeſſion tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his attrition into contrition. And thus poore ſoules, being beguiled with this blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and benighting Doctrine, truſt ſo farre vpon this their externall Confeſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Abſolution, that they neglect inward repentance, and ſo ſticke faſt in their ſinnes, thinking that they haue done their part, when they haue gone ouer the beadroule of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10339:25"/>their ſinnes, and ſo receiued Abſolution. But thoſe good ſoules, that put not this ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in any ſuch power of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution (which in trueth cannot deriue from the Goſpel any Sacramentall operation) and certainely perſwade themſelues, that they haue no other meanes of remedy, then true hearty repentante, they relie vpon that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and make requeſt to God for it by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and feruent prayers, vſing alſo other helpes, whereto the Scriptures direct vs, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, giuing of almes, and other workes of charitie: Not that theſe doe ſatisfie for the puniſhment, as the Romaniſts vainly teach, (For God, when hee pardoneth the ſinne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth alſo the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as is moſt cleare in Scripture) but, becauſe theſe are fruits of inward Repentance, and parts of outward; and ſo make way for remiſſion of ſinnes. But the Romiſh prepoſterous courſe (miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and miſ-doing in the darke night of this error) worketh cleane contrary, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the cart before the horſe, firſt granting remiſſion, and afterward impoſing workes of repentance, which indeede ſhould goe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10339:26"/>before repentance, and much more before remiſſion. And by this reckoning the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſoules, when they thinke themſelues moſt free, then remaine moſt bound, and vnpardoned before the throne of God. This deuiſe therfore of Sacramentall Confeſſion, and Sacramentall Abſolution, as they terme it, as it is pernicious, ſo it hath the brand of nouelty, being firſt impoſed by Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the third: After the entrance whereof, the forme of true repentance is very hardly to bee found in the Churches ſubiect to the Papacy. O how much better were it for a ſinner not to goe to Confeſſion, but onely when he findeth himſelfe in his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience rightly diſpoſed, &amp; to be in the ſtate of true repentance? For the often frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Confeſſion, as it is vſed, and receiuing of Abſolution, ſuch as it is, makes a ſinfull wretch feede himſelfe with ſhadowes, and ſeeme to himſelfe to giue his conſcience ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſatisfaction. Whereupon he, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſerable eſtate, wherin he remains, neuer thinketh ſeriouſly of true repentance. Whereas, if hee had not that vaine imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10339:26"/>which ſerueth him but to cloake his ſinnes, he would finde himſelfe to bee yet in the eſtate of ſinne, and would earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke himſelfe of the true remedy, namely inward ſincere repentance, which, without any other confeſſion, or abſolution, cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth our ſinnes, as fully appeareth out of the holy Scriptures, and Fathers. It is therefore an errour very grieuous, and hurtful to the ſoule, to beleeue that theſe externall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances conferre remiſſion of ſinnes, and that they are neceſſary therunto. What ſhall we ſay of ſo many other meere externall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, whereto the people is moſt ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inclined, as holy water, beades, croſſes, conſecrated Images, Papall and Epiſcopall benedictions, Stations, Pardons, the new found hoode of the Carmelites, called the <hi>Habitell,</hi> the whipcoards of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> the girdles of the Cordeliers, the viſiting of ſuch a Church in ſuch dayes, or of theſe and theſe altars, and reliques, nay the very hearing of Maſſes, and anealing him, that lies a dying? Theſe, and ſuch like other outward ſhewes, doe fill, and puffe vp the ſoule with a very
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10339:27"/>ſurfet of an imaginary, and falſe deuotion. Wherupon men thinke not of purging their conſciences, of conſummating their faith, of inflaming their charity towards God, and toward their neighbor; they buſie not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about repenting of their ſinnes, and performing thoſe internall actions, wherein the eſſentiall part of our reconciliation with God, and eternall ſaluation doth conſiſt. And when a man hath once in a day ſigned himſelfe with the ſigne of the Croſſe, and ſayd ouer his <hi>Pater Noster,</hi> (which he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands neuer a whit) together with his <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> and hath heard Maſſe, why then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth he is a Saint, and hath learned enough in religion: and ſo faſtning vpon theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he ſets vp his reſt on them for his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And, if at any time they can enſnare an vngrounded Proteſtant, and winne him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to their partie, they thinke him very well furniſhed, if he can beleeue in the Pope, and will heare Maſſe; vpon this preſently, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more adoe, they declare him to bea moſt perfect Catholique. Let them not heere tell me, that the inwards of the ſoule are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10339:27"/>vp, and whetted by theſe outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For experience ſheweth the contrary, that the people, when they haue tired them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with viſiting ſo many altars, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo many Maſſes, with chewing ouer ſo many halfe-ſcores of <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> in running ouer al the Roſary, when they haue ſo and ſo many times kiſſed the Croſſe, and haue bin in Proceſſions, they looke no further, but deeme themſelues to bee all holy, and that they need nothing elſe; and yet they goe on in their ſinnes: nay, ſuch as theſe, for the moſt part, become in their inward, worſe euery day then other; and for all this, mend not their liues, nor ſettle themſelues to true repentance.
<note place="margin">Lament. 4.4.</note> Of theſe poore ſtarued ſoules we may ſay, <hi>Paruuli petierunt panem, &amp; non est qui frangat eis. The children called for bread, and there is none to breake it to them.</hi> And if they affoord them any ſcraps of bread, it muſt not be the true bread of life, but in ſtead of wholeſome and nouriſhing bread made of wheat, they giue them bread made of bran, or acornes: and, to keepe them from ſence of hunger, they ſtuffe them vp with ſwines
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10339:28"/>meat, the huskes, and ſhales of theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, and ſuperſtitious deuotions. What now adayes carrieth away the noiſe in their pulpits? what, but the Papacie, Purgatory, and Indulgences, and other the like ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions? Here one extolls a certaine Image of the bleſſed Virgin to bee ſeene in his Church, which makes miracles Gods plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but theſe feates are either imagined, or dreamed of, or elſe contriued by impoſture. There another ſtands vpon the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a certaine wodden wonder-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Crucifixe, making a moſter of it with a troope of lighted Torches about it: and, the more to endeare it, hee withdraweth the Curtaines but ſeldome, and openeth the Shrine at a few ſet times in the yeere. Otherwhere others doe the like, and all for the ſame end; namely to allure the ſimple people to flocke to them, and ſo to worke vpon their purſes. O miſery of corruption! O night of darkeneſſe!</p>
               <p>I paſſe now to the third generall error, and it is this: That the thunderbolt of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication darted out by the Pope is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10339:28"/>euermore very terrible, and that it ſtrikes deepe, wounding the ſoule, and tumbling it downe-right into hell, if the Popes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be not obeyed. True it is, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop within his owne Biſhopricke (no leſſe then the Pope within the Biſhopricke of Rome) hath power to excommunicate grieuous, and ſcandalous offenders, either debarring them of Eccleſiaſticall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with other Chriſtian people, vntill they amend; or, if the caſe bee deſperate, caſting them out of the Church, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them off from the body of Chriſt, as dead and rotten members. But whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuch Excommunications are ſent out without iuſt, yea and moſt weighty cauſe, they more hurt him that thundereth them out, then them, againſt whom they are bent. It muſt needes therefore be a great folly, to ſtand in feare of the Popes Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication whenſoeuer hee threatens in this ſort, Either beleeue whatſoeuer I ſay, or I will excommunicate you: Either ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to be ſupreme Lord of all the world both in ſpirituall, and temporall matters,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10339:29"/>or you ſhall be excommunicated: Either acknowledge, and worſhip mee for a god vpon earth, or you ſhall bee held for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. To bring his owne ends to paſſe, he worketh in this ſort: hee compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth men both to beleeue, and alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme whatſoeuer he pleaſe: hee forelayeth meanes to keepe ſimple ouerfearefull men in awe, ſo that they ſhall not dare to ſtand out in their owne defence againſt his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie. By theſe vaine terrors he taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vſe of many excellent bookes, therefore prohibited, becauſe they lay open his colluſions. Neuertheleſſe this rule is certaine, and infallible, whoſouer, walking vprightly in the ſight of God, with ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heart, and honeſt intention, readeth bookes, not out of carnall curioſity, but out of deſire to learne, and to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene truth and falſehood, and to the end that hee may not alwaies remaine blind, let him not feare a whit, nor make any account of ſuch Excommunication, which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeparate any man from God, vnleſſe hee hath in his owne heart firſt ſeparated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10339:29"/>from him. Without doubt, the Pope maketh great vſe of this ſcarcrow feare of his Excommunications, as a fit engine to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force many a falſehood, and to hide out of the way many truths, for the vpholding of his owne moſt vndue, and vſurped great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. This indeede hath bene his weapon, wherewith hee long ſince hath layde about him; but it hath beene retorted backe vpon him by many holy men, who haue not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to laugh at his falſe thunderclaps, bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out by great abuſe without neceſſity, or iuſt cauſe at all, and haue made him to giue ouer with ſhame enough. Let vs now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore render our thankes to God, who hath reſcued vs <hi>de ore Leonis,</hi> out of the mouth of the Lion, and <hi>de nube erroris</hi> out of the cloud of error, ſo that the enemy cannot leade vs into ſuch deepe darkeneſſe, as he yet doth many ſoules miſerably captiuated to him. And therefore to vs, <hi>Nox praeceſsit, The night is past.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dies autem appropinquauit; But the day hath approached.</hi> To theſe foure nights there are as many daies correſpondent. The firſt is of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10339:30"/>the knowledge of God, and of the holy Chriſtian faith, the ſhadowes being diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the veiles taken away by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, when that which lay hidde vnder types, and darke reſemblances, was manifeſted by the light of the Goſpel. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it without myſterious ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that at the very paſſion of Chriſt <hi>the veile of the Temple was rent from the toppe downe to the bottome.</hi> For the ſacred myſteries of God were not now to remaine any longer cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned vp, inaſmuch as at the appearing of the Sunne of righteouſnes all thoſe cloudes and darkenes vaniſhed away; cleere reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beeing then made to vs of the vnity in Nature, and trinity in Perſons in God, and of the Redeemer, the true and naturall Sonne of God, in whom are two Natures, the one diuine, the other humane, ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the diuine Perſon of the Word. He is in ſubſtance, and cleere ſignification the foreſhadowed ſpotleſſe Lambe of God: He is the true Sacrifice, which was hidden, and veyled in the ſacrifices of the old Law, the moſt precious ſacrifice offered vp vpon the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10339:30"/>altar of the Croſſe for our ſinnes; whereto no other ſacrifice is now to ſucceed,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> beſides the reaſonable ſeruice of our ſoules, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and perpetuall thankeſgiuing, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of his moſt holy name.</p>
               <p>The ſecond day is the day of Grace, with full remiſſion of all our ſinnes in holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, the Church beeing ſanctified, and cleanſed by the Lauer of water in the Word. Of thoſe, that receiued Chriſt by the preaching of the Apoſtles, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee were ſometimes darkeneſse, but now yee are light in the Lord, who commanded light to ſhine out of darkeneſſe.</hi> To the Gentiles the light of Nature, and to the Iewes the Law did point at what ought to be done; but neither the one, nor the other gaue grace, and ſtrength to worke well,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth:
<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.</note> For that Nature beeing corrupted was ouer nimble to runne headlong into ſinne. But the grace of Chriſt helpeth our naturall weakeneſſe, and helpeth vs to bee ſet free, and preſerued from ſinne, and therefore, <hi>Hic dies appropinquauit, The day hath approached.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:10339:31"/>
               <p>The third day is the day of watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diligence, and care. The wild, and ſauage beaſts watch moſt of all in the night time, forraging then for their prey. On the contrarie, man r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſeth himſelfe in the night, and goeth about his buſineſſe in the day time.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſuiſti tenebras, &amp; facta eſt nox, in ipſa pertranſibunt omnes beſtiae Syluae, &amp;c. Thou madeſt darkeneſſe, and it is night, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the beaſts of the Foreſt creepe forth. The young Lions roare after their prey, and ſeek their meat of God. When the Sunne riſeth, they retire, and couch in their dennes.</hi> It is not ſo with man: For when the Sunne is vp, then <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit homo ad opus ſuum, &amp;c. Man goeth forth to his worke, and to his labour till the Euening.</hi> It is the propertie of beaſts, and thoſe the moſt harmefull, to make the day their time of ſleepe, and the night their time of labour: ſo of men, thoſe that employ themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euill,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.19.</note> ſhun the light. <hi>Men loued darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more then the light: For their workes were euill. Euerie man that doeth euill, hateth the light, and commeth not to the light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be reproued.</hi> But thoſe men, that take not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10339:31"/>after ſuch wild beaſts, employ themſelues in good works, as much as they can, whileſt they haue the oportunitie of the light, and ſpend not the day in ſleepe, but make their aduantage of the time.
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>He, that doeth the trueth, commeth to the light, that his deeds might be made manifeſt; that they are wrought in God.</hi> Chriſt our inſtructor, and enſample, ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him, that ſent mee, whileſt it is day. The night commeth, when no man can worke.</hi> How much more ought wee euerie of vs to ſay the ſame of our ſelues, to whom S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Hora eſt iam nos de ſomno ſurgere.</hi> Now it is time for vs to ariſe from ſleepe. Whileſt the day of this life laſteth we are to buſie our ſelues in good workes, and to ſhew that we haue a liuely faith. <hi>Venit nox; The night commeth, wherein no man can worke.</hi> It is a meere folly to expect (as the Romaniſts doe) that others ſhould worke for vs, and apply their works to vs when wee are dead and gone; that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould faſt for vs, purchaſe S. <hi>Gregories</hi> Maſſes, and ſeeke out priuiledged altars, and procure Indulgences for vs, <hi>Per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10339:32"/>interceſſion,</hi> they ſeeke out priuiledged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars: But the night ouertakes them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no man can worke; ſurely neyther him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in perſon, nor others to his vſe. Our journey is ended: we by death arriue at our long home, either of eternall Saluation, or of endleſſe damnation; there is no meane eſtate betweene theſe two.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.3.</note> 
                  <hi>If the tree fall toward the South or toward the North, in the place where the treefalleth, there it ſhall be.</hi> Therefore whileſt the day holdes, doe that, which thou haſt to doe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>The dead prayſe not the Lord, neither any that goe downe into the place of ſilence;</hi> that is, into the graue. <hi>But we</hi> (that liue) <hi>let vs prayſe the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>The graue cannot praiſe thee, death can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not celebrate thee, they that goe downe into the pit cannot hope for thy trueth. The liuing, the liuing, he ſhall praiſe thee.</hi> The fourth kind of day, is the day of pure &amp; meere trueth. <hi>The night is paſsed</hi> of ſo many errors, which with the Papacy haue crept into the Papall Churches: and to vs, by the grace of the Almighty, the day is arriued. He that liued vnder the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy might, and ought then to ſay in his prayers to God, <hi>Emitte lucem tuam, &amp; verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10339:32"/>tuam. Send foorth thy light, and thy trueth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 43.3.</note> But he, that is freed thence, muſt inſiſt vpon that, which followeth, <hi>Ipſa me deduxerunt, &amp; adduxerunt in montem ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuum, &amp; in taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naculatua. They haue led me, and brought me vnto thy holy hill, and to thy tabernacles.</hi> Here (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethren) heere in this Kingdome wee haue the hill of God, which is rayſed vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, and ſtandeth diſcoaſted farre enough from the ſinke, and myre of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall corruptions. Here are the tabernacles, and tents of the armies of the Lord of hoſts pitcht in goodly aray, and furniſhed for the confronting all oppoſite forces. Heere the light of the trueth is freely, and openly let in. Heere the holy Scriptures are moſt exactly ſtudied. Here are great multitudes of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, and aboue all, the moſt learned the Anoynted of the Lord, a King, who is the wonder of the Kings of the earth, a match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe paterne to all the Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome, of great zeale in purging, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing, and mainteining Chriſts holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Heere the ſincere word of God is taught plentifully. Here the Biſhops are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10339:33"/>learned, religious, and vigilant ouer their flocks. Here the Prieſts are euery way ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and very skilfull in the cure of ſoules. Heere the people are very zealous, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently addicted to holy and ſpirituall due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Thanks therefore be to God, who after the night of ſo many errors, hath ſent foorth his light and trueth, which haue led me, and brought me into his holy hill, and to his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles. And ſo reioycing in the Lord, I ſay againe to my ſelfe, and to you, my brethren, <hi>The night is paſſed, and the day is at hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere perhaps ſome man may demaund of mee, why S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>day is at hand,</hi> and not rather that it is already come: which doubt ſeemeth the greater vpon the words, which goe before, <hi>Nunc propior eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraſalus, quàm cum credidimus; Now is our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation neerer, then when wee beleeued.</hi> Heere therefore the approach of the day is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of ſaluation; and the day, and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are to bee taken to ſignifie one, and the ſame, and by conſequence beſides that day, and ſaluation, which is Chriſt, and his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, &amp; beſides that day and ſaluation, which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10339:33"/>ſignifieth grace, and the remiſſion of ſinnes, S. <hi>Paul</hi> vnderſtandeth yet another day, and another ſaluation, which he declareth to bee come neerer at the time of his writing this Epiſtle to them, then it was when they firſt receiued the Faith, and holy Baptiſme, with remiſſion of ſinnes. By this ſaluation, which is ſaid to haue come neerer, <hi>Lyra</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Saluation brought in by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, as being neerer, then it was before his comming. But neither S. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor theſe Chriſtians, to whom hee wrote it, were beleeuers before the comming of Chriſt. And yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith plainely, <hi>quàm cum credidimus,</hi> that is, then when we began to beleeue in Chriſt. Saint <hi>Chyſoſtome</hi> by this Saluation vnderſtandeth the generall reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which ſhall be at the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, at Doomeſday: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with S. <hi>Paul</hi> awaketh the faithfull, to make them watchfull, and ready for that generall Iudgement, which in the very Apoſtles times was by many deemed to be very nigh at hand. But it is better for vs to interprete this admonition of the Apoſtle concerning
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10339:34"/>Death, and the particular iudgement of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man; and euery of vs to ſay to our ſelues, and to one another, <hi>Noſter dies appropinqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, &amp; propior eſt Salus noſtra; Our day is at hand, and our Saluation is neerer,</hi> becauſe the day of our death comes on euery moment neerer, &amp; neerer. Let vs therfore, my brethren, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that at the comming of that laſt day, Chriſt may finde vs prepared:
<note place="margin">Matth. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>For yee know not at what houre your Maſter will come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> Be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, as the fiue wiſe Virgins were ready, and entred in with the Spouſe to the wedding. And let vs take heede, that befalles vs not, which the fiue fooliſh virgins found, who were for euer ſhut out of doores from the wedding, with that terrible anſwere, <hi>Neſcio vos, I know you not.</hi> And therefore <hi>horaest nos de ſomno ſurgere.</hi> It is high time for vs to awake from ſleepe, foraſmuch as <hi>Dies appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquauit; The day is nigh at hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abijciamus ergo operatenebrarum;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> Let vs put off this blacke ſuite. The firſt worke of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or rather that darkneſſe, which God in the firſt Creation of the world did diuide from the light,
<note place="margin">De ciuitat. Dei. lib. 11. cap. 19.</note> is by S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expounded
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:10339:34"/>to be the euill Angels; who are alſo ſtiled by S. <hi>Paul, The Princes of the darkneſſe of this world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> Theſe wee haue openly renounced in our Baptiſme; and yet they ceaſe not to ſet vpon vs. <hi>Reſiſt the Diuell and hee will flie from you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames. 4.</note> He that trauaileth in the night eaſily falleth into the hands of theeues, and cut-throats, and is moſt commonly robbed of that hee hath, and ſometime of his life alſo.
<note place="margin">Iohn 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>If a man walke in the day, he ſtumbleth not, becauſe he ſeeth the light of this world. But if a man walke in the night he ſtumbleth, becauſe there is no light in him.</hi> The Diuels are theſe night-theeues, and ſomtime alſo day-roauers, <hi>Meridiani,</hi> euen in the noone day. Their ſnares are temptations, and ſinne their priſon. If therfore we would not fall into their hands, and become ſlaues to the kingdome of darkneſſe, let vs caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the workes of darkneſſe, let vs walke in the day in our Sauiour Chriſts companie, and wee ſhall not need to ſtand in feare of them. <hi>Scuto circundabit te veritas eius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.4.</note> 
                  <hi>non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebis à timore nocturno. A ſagitta volante in die, à negotio perambulante in tenebris, ab incurſu &amp; daemonio meridiano. Cadent à latere tuo mille,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10339:35"/>&amp; decem milliad dextris tuis, ad te autem non ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propinquabit. His truth ſhall ſhield thee as a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Thou ſhalt not bee afraid of the feare of the night, nor of the arrow that flieth by day, of the worke that walketh in the darke, of inuaſion, nor of the diuell of the midday. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand: but it ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi> The workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are ſleepe, dreames, and idleneſſe. Let vs ſhake off theſe alſo.
<note place="margin">Matth. 13.25.</note> For <hi>whileſt men are aſleepe the enemie ſoweth the Tares.</hi> And the vaine dreames of worldly proiects doe ſo intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the braine, that wee forget our owne ſoules, and things eternall. That miſerable worldling was in a dreame, when he ſayd, <hi>I will pull downe my barnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12.19.</note> 
                  <hi>and build vp greater. I will ſay vnto my ſoule, Soule thou haſt much goods layed vp for many yeeres. Liue at eaſe, eat, drinke, and take thy paſtime.</hi> But this dreame was very ſhort; for preſently hee heard that voice from God, <hi>O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee.</hi> Let vs therfore ſhake off ſuch dreames as theſe, together with all idleneſſe, and ſluggiſhneſſe in things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, and his heauenly trueth. It
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10339:35"/>muſt bee accounted among the workes of darkneſſe, if we be poſſeſſed with a nightly, drowſie ſilence in Gods buſineſſe, during this cleare day of trueth. Let vs therfore caſt away this ſtupidity, let vs breake this ſilence.
<note place="margin">Iſai 58.</note> 
                  <hi>Clama, neceſſes.</hi> Crie out aloud, and ſpare not, ſayth the Prophet. So did S. <hi>Paul</hi> as he teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of himſelfe, <hi>Mundus ſum à ſanguine &amp;c. I am pure from the blood of all men.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 20.26.</note> 
                  <hi>For I haue not ſhunned to declare vnto you, all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of GOD.</hi> Therefore if we alſo doe not thus, we ſhall not be guiltleſſe of the blood of thoſe ſoules, which periſh through our ſilence. Let vs praiſe God with our voice, let vs publiſh abroad his truth.
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Teaching and admoniſhing our ſelues in Pſalmes, and Hymmes, and ſpirituall ſongs ſinging with grace in our hearts to the Lord.</hi> Let vs therefore caſt away theſe, and all other workes of darkeneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et induamur arma lucis.</hi> As ſoone as wee haue quitte our ſelues of our blacke, and dolefull apparell, it remaines, that wee doe not any while remaine naked, but foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with put on our cleare and lightſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10339:36"/>
                  <hi>Let vs put on the armour of light.</hi> It is not hard to finde what this armour of light is. Our Sauiour Chriſt, ſpeaking of himſelfe, ſaide,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.12. and 8.46. and 9 5.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the light of the world. As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world. I am come a light into the world.</hi> And our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here declareth expreſſelie, that he meant Chriſt to bee this our lightſome cloathing, when hee addeth afterward <hi>Put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Before that Chriſt came, God, as I told you, held the light hidden in his hand. But, after his comming, his beloued diſciple deſcribeth the holy Church in theſe words; <hi>A Woman clad with the Sunne, and the Moone vnder her feete.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 12.1.</note> And the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with St. <hi>Pauls</hi> exhorting euery Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to <hi>Put on Ieſus Chriſt, and take no thought for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts of it.</hi> The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Moone vnder ourfeete, is the contemning of the fleſhly vanity of things temporall and tranſitory, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per duty of a Chriſtian. And euen this, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here ſaith to the Romanes <hi>The night is paſt, let vs put on the armour of light;</hi> hee ſaith in other words to the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10339:36"/>
                  <hi>Awake thou that ſleepest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some curious braines haue coniectured, that <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> when hee was ſhutte vppe in the Arke, and could not haue light by the little window thereof, (which alſo was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally kept ſhut) vſed a Carbuncle, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more radiant precious Stone, to giue light in the Arke. And what ſtone can be ſo bright to enlighten our darkenes, whileſt we float to ſaue vs from the deluge of ſinne, as Chriſt? <hi>Petra autem erat Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4. Ioh. 1.9.</note> And that ſtone is Chriſt, who alſo is <hi>the true light, that enlighteneth euery man that commeth into the world.</hi> Hee is the moſt reſplendent, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Gemme: Let vs fell all to purchaſe it. He that hath not Chriſt before him, let him not looke for the light.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 127.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Vanum est vobís ante lucem ſurgere. It is but loſt labour for you to riſe before the daylight.</hi> He that thinketh himſelfe able to riſe out of darkeneſſe, and obſcure night of ſinne and infidelity, before that Chriſt ſ end forth the day-ſpring of grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his heart, ſurely hee is in an idle conceit,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10339:37"/>and dreameth in the night of a great errour. If thou of thy ſelfe wilt needes get vp before the light, thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to remaine in the darke. Hee that would walke in ſafety, and in the light, let him riſe indeede, but hee muſt riſe with Chriſt, and follow Chriſt whitherſoeuer he leadeth:
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.14.</note> and this is to <hi>put on the Lord Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> was ſometime cloathed with the goodly white Roabe of innocencie, and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall iuſtice. But (alas) being miſſeled by the counſaile giuen him by the Serpent the Prince of darkeneſſe, he fell into the hands of theeues,
<note place="margin">Luke 10.30.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſtripped him of his rayment, and wounded him, and departed, leauing him halfe dead.</hi> But behold, the good Samaritane doth not only cure his wounds, but alſo couereth his nakedneſſe, vouchſafing himſelfe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a garment vnto him. <hi>Therefore put yee on the Lord Ieſus.</hi> This is that wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without which whoſoeuer preſenteth himſelfe to the Table of the Lord, ſhall bee thruſt out of doores <hi>in tenebras exteriores,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 22.13.</note> 
                  <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vtter darkeneſſe.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10339:37"/>this faire Roabe, this nuptiall Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was then at making for vs.
<note place="margin">Eſai. 61.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I will greatly reioyce in the Lord, my ſoule ſhall bee ioyfull in my God. For hee hath cloathed mee with the garments of ſaluation: hee hath couered mee with the Roabe of righteouſeneſſe, as a bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome decketh himſelfe with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth her ſelfe with her iewels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Induamur arma lucis. Let vs put on the armor of light.</hi> Hee ſaith not let vs put on the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of light, but the armour of light. For Chriſt arrayeth vs, <hi>non ad pompam, ſed ad pugnam,</hi> not to ſet vs out in an empty and vaine ſhew, but to furniſh, and ſecure vs for combat, the whole life of a Chriſtian beeing a warfare. Of the moſt accompliſhed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Antiochus</hi> it is related in the hiſtory of the Machabees, that,
<note place="margin">Machab.</note> 
                  <hi>when the Sunne ſhone vpon the ſhields of gold, and braſſe, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines gliſtred therewith, and ſhined like lampes of fire.</hi> It is another manner of luſtre, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which this armour of light, worne by a Chriſtian, doth dart forth on euery ſide vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eyes of God himſelfe, and of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10339:38"/>Angels, and bleſſed ſoules. <hi>For the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our warfare are not carnall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>but mighty through God, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds, caſting downe imaginations, and euery high thing, that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt.</hi> And ſo Chriſt is our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, our ſtrength, our defence, our cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, our conquerer, and in the end our both rewarder, and reward. Behold the armour of light.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Put on the whole armour of God, that yee may bee able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the diuell. For we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt the rulers of the darkeneſse of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places. Put on the breſtplate of righteouſeneſſe, — take the ſhield of faith, — the helmet of ſaluation, the ſword of the ſpirit which is the word of God.</hi> I hope in God, by the helpe alſo of your godly prayers, deare brethren, that his heauenly Maieſty will reach foorth to mee, and direct in my hand this ſword of his word, wherewith, as I haue begun, ſo I may bee enabled to hold
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10339:38"/>on the combat againſt the Rulers of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the ſetting free ſo many poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſoules from a many of errours, and that I may alſo put this ſword into their owne hands, with which they of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues may worke their owne freedome from that yoake of Tyranny, which lieth ſo heauy vpon them.</p>
               <p>Let vs all put on the armour of light, and in ſpeciall, you my brethren of Italy. For if we would all with ioynt endeuour furniſh our ſelues with this armour, wee might the better hope for a glorious victory. We ſhall indeed put on the armour of light, if, vpon the reforming of Religion, and deteſtation of errors in doctrine, we ſhall lead an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary life, full of good edification, keeping our ſelues a farre off from ſin, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout in prayers, frequent in hearing, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God, and in performance of other ſpirituall exerciſes, eſpecially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the holy Communion, and alſo ſhall ſhew our ſelues fruitfull in good workes. <hi>So let your light ſhine before men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:10339:39"/>ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi> What ſhall it auaile vs to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and not to reforme our liues withall? To beleeue aright, and to doe that which is wrong will ſtand vs in little ſteed, nay it will ſinke vs the deeper, into Hell.
<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> He that knoweth the will of God, and doeth it not, <hi>ſhalbe beaten with the more ſtripes. The Diuels alſo beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>and tremble.</hi> It is a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpeech among the Papiſts, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer leaueth their party, and ioyneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Reformed Churches, doth it for the loue of carnall libertie, and that he may lead a licentious life. It lieth vpon vs for our part to giue them no occaſion of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull ſlanders; and to array our ſelues with ſuch lightſome, and glittering armour, as may dazle their eies, and confound them: ſo that they may be forced to confeſſe, that in the Reformed Churches, there is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined and fruitfull profeſſion of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of life alſo; and that there men liue in the true feare of God, in true godlineſſe, and true deuotion, free from ſcandall. <hi>Put
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:10339:39"/>yee on therefore, as the elect of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>holy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, the bowels of mercy kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekneſſe, long ſuffering, forbearing one another, and forgiuing one another, if any man haue a quarrell againſt any. And aboue all theſe things put on charity, which is the bond of perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> If we put on the armour of light, wee ſhall become <hi>the children of light,</hi> and enioy alſo the fruit of light.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.9.</note> 
                  <hi>For the fruit</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Alias of the Spirit.</note> 
                  <hi>of the light is in all goodneſſe, and righteouſneſſe, and trueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which of vs knoweth not that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are ſtiled, <hi>The children of the light?</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe God himſelfe is light. Whereupon our Sauiour Chriſt vſeth this reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the children of this world, that is, the children of darkneſſe <hi>are wiſer then the children of light:</hi> And admoniſheth vs in this maner: <hi>While yee haue light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 12.36. Epheſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>beleeue in the light, that ye may be the children of light.</hi> In like maner S. <hi>Paul: Walke as the children of light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.</note> Becauſe yee are <hi>the children of light, and the ſonnes of God.</hi> And therfore here he exhorteth vs: <hi>Let vs put on the armour of light.</hi> A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſheweth quickly by his life, whether he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10339:40"/>be the ſonne of God, or no. The Eagle with his ſtrong and cleare eyes is able, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to looke directly vpon the Sunne, and by this eſſay ſhee is wont to prooue her yong ones: namely if they be both able, and willing to fixe their ſight vpon the flaming circle of the Sunne, then ſhe takes them for her owne: but if they will nor gaze vpon the Sunne, but turne their eyes away from the beames thereof, then ſhee caſteth them out of her neſt, as a baſtard degenerating, and changeling brood. So our heauenly Father, who <hi>as an Eagle ſtirreth vp her neſt, fluttereth oner her yong,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings,</hi> doth prooue vs, whether we delight to looke vp on him being our light, and, if he finde, that we <hi>ſeeke thoſe things which are about,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.2.</note> and make our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhine with the cleare white of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, of due obedience to him, and of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imiration of him, then hee holdeth vs for his owne vndoubted offpring, and for true children of the light. But if he finde vs <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugas</hi> to ſhrinke backe from the light, and to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:10339:40"/>turne away from beholding our Sunne of righteouſneſſe, compoſing our ſelues to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold only <hi>thoſe things that are vpon the earth,</hi> then hee caſteth vs off, for ſo many Owles and Battes, that loue the darke, and cannot abide the light.</p>
               <p>That light, from whence wee are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect theſe good effects muſt be Chriſt only. By no Planet, or Starre, other then the Sun, can true and pure gold bee begotten in the bowels of the earth; or fine Orient Pearle in the ſhels of fiſhes. Let the Alchymiſts ſweat, and ſpend themſelues in labouring to make gold by artificiall meanes, and heat, diuers from the heat of the Sunne: They ſhall bring foorth nothing, but falſe Alchymicall gold, of no worth. Whoſoeuer ſeeketh for ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and grace (which is the true and precious gold, and the riches of all our ſpirituall good) from any other Planet, then from the true Sunne Chriſt, he troubleth himſelfe in vaine. When we are clad with this light, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with Chriſt, we ſhall be a moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſight to the eyes of our heauenly King,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:10339:41"/>and haue cauſe to preſume of victory ouer the Prince of darkneſſe.
<note place="margin">Eſther. 5.</note> So <hi>Heſter</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed in royall robes did winne the heart of <hi>Aſſuerus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith 10.3.</note> So <hi>Iudith,</hi> being clad <hi>with garments of gladneſſe,</hi> obtained that notable victory vpon <hi>Holophernes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere biddeth all the faithfull, <hi>Put on the armour of light;</hi> ſurely (that which much affecteth me) he ſpeaketh the ſame in more ſpecial &amp; effectuall maner to vs Prieſts and Miniſters of Chriſt. For euen long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, God did ſufficiently declare, that his Miniſters were to be clothed with light and whiteneſſe.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 44.17.</note> 
                  <hi>When they enter in at the gates of the inner Court, they ſhalbe cloathed with linnen garments, and no wollen ſhall come vpon them.</hi> He that is to miniſter in the Sanctuary, muſt not haue wooll about him, being a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity pertayning to a beaſt (that is, hee muſt not carry <hi>affectus animales,</hi> carnall, and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections) but white, and pure linnen, which is the ſymbole of the brightneſſe of all vertues, good example, and perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Sacerdotes tui induantur iuſtitiam. Let
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:10339:41"/>thy Prieſts be clothed with righteouſnes. Et num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damini, qui fertis vaſa Domini:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>Be yee cleane that cary the veſſels of the Lord.</hi> And what elſe is ſignified to vs by the white linnen gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherewith (according to the moſt ancient rites, &amp; laudable cuſtome of the pure and yet, yet-uncorrupted Church) we are cloathed, whileſt we exerciſe our ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but that it is our duety to put on the light, and to ſhine in all purity of life? This white habite putteth vs in mind, that chiefly of vs that is ſpoken by our Sauiour;
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>No man lighteth a candle, &amp; puttteh it vnder a buſhell, but ſetteth it vp in a candleſtick, &amp; it giueth light to all that are in the houſe.</hi> They that are in the holy Miniſtery, ought now to ſerue for a Pillar of a cloud by day, and a Pillar of fire by night, to guide the Army of the Lord into the land of promiſe: They are the eyes of the Church. I may therefore apply to the Church that ſpeach vttered by our Sauiour;
<note place="margin">Mar. 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucerna cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris eſtoculus. The eye is the light of the body.</hi> And (as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> a moſt worthy Biſhop hereupon inferreth,)
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 30. apud Baſilium.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucerna autem Eccleſiae
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:10339:42"/>est Epiſcopus. A Biſhop is the Light or lampe, of his Church.</hi> Therefore O Church, <hi>If thine eye be ſingle, thy whole body ſhalbe full of light: But if thine eye be euill, thy whole body ſhalbe full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. If therefore the light, that is in thee, be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, how great is that darkenes?</hi> The Papall Churches (alas) know too wel by wofull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that from darke and euil eyes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that palpable darknes, wherin they are held. Their Prelates, eſpecially he that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe Prelate of Prelats, are naughty pour-blind eyes, (nor do I except my ſelfe, as I was heretofore, being blind with them for company) eyes full of earthly duſt, which are bent onely to poare downeward vpon the earth. And ſo the diſtreſſed Churches vnder them remaine clouded vp in darkneſſe. But let vs thanke GOD, that here the eyes are all pure, and ſimple: and thereupon <hi>Totum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> the whole body of this happy Church <hi>lucidum eſt,</hi> is cleare, and bright.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I ſpoken of light, and of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of day, and of night. In this life, in this valley of teares we are much ſubiect to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:10339:42"/>darkneſſe. Let vs therefore pray the Author and Fountaine of all light, that after this darkeſome life, he would conduct vs vp to that holy, and heauenly Hieruſalem,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.23.</note> which <hi>hath no neede of the Sunne, neither of the Moone to ſhine in it: For the glory of God doeth lighten it, and the Lambe is the light thereof.</hi> To whom be praiſe, and glory for euermore.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.14.</note> and the loue of God, and the fellowſhip of the holy Ghoſt be with vs all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
